{"tossups": [{"question": "In one anecdote, this book\u2019s author beheaded two women when he was asked to supervise a battle between 180 courtesans. This book postulates the following hierarchy of targets: ideas, then alliances, then armies, then cities. This book\u2019s first chapter, about planning, lays out five fundamental factors in its title discipline including seasonal changes and terrain. Understanding battlefield geography is advocated in, for ten points, what strategy book written during the Spring and Autumn Period by Sun Tzu?", "answer": "The<b> Art of War</b> (or Sunzi<b> bingfa</b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. In the final days of this event, Operation Thunder was called off when Viktor Karpukhin believed there would be too many civilian deaths. This event\u2019s failure led to the suicide of Boris Pugo and arrest of KGB chief Vladimir Kryuchkov. The State Committee on the State of Emergency was opposed by civilians erecting barricades outside the Russian White House during this event, where the Gang of Eight was thwarted by a speech atop a tank given by Boris Yeltsin. For ten points, name this coup that targeted the final leader of the Soviet Union.", "answer": "<b> August</b> Coup (or<b> August</b> Putsch; accept descriptions of the 1991<b> coup</b> against Mikhail <b>Gorbachev</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This woman was represented by James Bradwell after she was involuntarily committed to Bellevue Place. This woman accused Elizabeth Keckley of violating her privacy by publishing<em> Behind the Scenes</em>. William Mumler took a photograph of this woman that supposedly shows the ghost of her dead husband in the background. Edwin Stanton ordered this woman to be removed from a room in the Peterson House, as she was too emotional over the shooting of her husband. For ten points, name this First Lady during the Civil War.", "answer": "Mary (Ann)<b> Todd Lincoln</b> (accept either or both surnames)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Yakama peoples\u2019 access to this industry was upheld in the Supreme Court case<em> U.S. v. Winans</em>. Under Grover Cleveland, the Retaliation Act and the Bayard-Chamberlain Treaty dealt with a dispute concerning this industry. Along with settling the<em> Alabama</em> claims, the 1871 Treaty of Washington allowed Americans access to this industry around Nova Scotia. The Grand Banks region has been a historical hotbed of, for ten points, what industry whose recreational \u201cfly\u201d version was popularized by Ernest Hemingway and other anglers?", "answer": "<b> fish</b>ing industry", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s namesake company created an advertisement that played off Emanuel Leutze\u2019s<em> Westward</em> <em>the Course of Empire Takes its Way</em>. This man sued John Henry Manny over patent infringement, but lost to a team of lawyers that included Edwin Stanton and Abraham Lincoln. This man drove rival Obed Hussey out of business by obtaining the rights to a cutter-bar mechanism. An 1837 invention of this man helped Midwest farmers harvest wheat more efficiently. For ten points, name this businessman and inventor of the mechanical reaper.", "answer": "Cyrus Hall<b> McCormick</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The<em> Vallum</em> was a ditch found near this structure, which was built before a similar structure intended to repel the Caledonians. The River Tyne was one endpoint of this structure, which was largely made of turf and built years before a structure further north was begun by Antoninus Pius. For ten points, name this defensive structure built by the third of the Five Good Emperors in Britain.", "answer": "<b> Hadrian\u2019s Wall</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This event was investigated by Hubert Williams, who assisted in compiling the Webster Report. A photograph taken during this event shows two men with handguns taking cover behind a forklift. During this event, Reginald Denny suffered 91 skull fractures after being pulled out of his truck and beaten. In the prelude to this event, George Holliday filmed a man being attacked by Timothy Wind and Lawrence Powell. The impassioned plea \u201cCan we all get along?\u201d was made during, for ten points, what 1992 race riot in California?", "answer": "<b> 1992 L</b>os<b> A</b>ngeles<b> riot</b>s (accept Rodney<b> King riots</b>; \u201c1992\u201d and \u201criot\u201d not needed after mentioned; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ruler had Stanislaw I installed in his place in the Treaty of Altranst\u00a8adt. During one campaign, this ruler deposed Augustus the Strong after crossing the D\u00a8una river. This ruler had the traitor Johann Patkul broken on the wheel for engineering an alliance against this man. Despite entering into an alliance with Ivan Mazepa, this ruler was completely defeated in a 1709 Battle against Peter the Great. For ten points, name this Swedish king who lost the Great Northern War.", "answer": "<b> Charles XII</b> of Sweden", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1933, the German Student Union carried out this action against Magnus Hirschfeld\u2019s Institute of Sex Research. The<em> Shi Jing</em> and<em> Shujing</em> were subject to this action on the suggestion of chancellor Li Si [lee see]. According to the<em> Records of the Grand Historian</em>, Confucian scholars were buried alive and this action was carried out in China. In 15th century Florence, Savonarola ordered, for ten points, what destructive action to be performed on \u201cVanities\u201d like Boccaccio\u2019s<em> Decameron</em>?", "answer": "<b> book burn</b>ing (accept equivalent descriptions; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cdestroying books\u201d or \u201cburning\u201d; prompt on \u201cBonfire of the Vanities\u201d between \u201c15th century\u201d and \u201cVanities\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this battle, Baroness Frederika Riedesel fled to the Marshall House, where refugees endured hours of bombardment. At this battle, Ebenezer Learned commanded the ineffective 1st Canadian Regiment. Simon Fraser was killed in this battle, whose field is home to the Boot Monument, which was erected to honor Benedict Arnold\u2019s sacrifice. The Battle of Freeman\u2019s Farm was part of, for ten points, what 1777 victory for Horatio Gates that prompted French intervention in the American Revolution?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Saratoga</b> (accept Battle of<b> Freeman\u2019s Farm</b> until mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In the last scene of this book, its narrator looks into a mirror in a hospital and sees a corpse staring back at him. This book was originally published in French with an introduction by its author\u2019s friend Francois Mauriac. The main character of this book refuses to celebrate the New Year after watching a child slowly die in a hanging. In this book, Moshe the Beadle warns the townspeople of Sighet of a series of coming atrocities, which claim the life of the narrator\u2019s father Chlomo. For ten points, name this Holocaust memoir by Elie Wiesel.", "answer": "<b> Night</b> (or<b> Nuit</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. It is thought that one of these documents states \u201cmy name is\u201dAlfred E. Neuman, the mascot of</b><em><b> Mad</b></em><b> Magazine. The final one of these documents explains a map with a compass set to magnetic north on Mount Diablo. Many (+) drawings in these documents were inspired by Harvey Balls. The meaning of the first of these documents was identified quickly by the supposition that it repeatedly used the word (*)</b> \u201ckill\u201d and the phrase\u201cI like killing.\u201d These documents were signed with a cross and a circle. For ten points, name these coded messages written by a San Francisco serial killer.", "answer": "the<b> Zodiac</b> Killer\u2019s<b> letter</b>s (accept<b> Zodiac cipher</b>s,<b> Zodiac cryptogram</b>s, etc.)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>When this figure\u2019s wife was harassed by the slime-spewing Long Eel, he cut its head off with a stone axe. This figure, who is the \u201cskillful\u201d member of a group of similarly named</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>\u201cforgetful\u201d siblings, once used a stone axe to kill a giant eel. This figure uses his</b> <b>grandmother\u2019s jawbone first to ensnare the sun into traveling more slowly and then to raise (*)</b> islands from the depths of the Pacific Ocean. For ten points, name this Polynesian trickster god who shares his name with the second-largest Hawaiian island.", "answer": "<b> Maui</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s father was killed at Piacenza after the Heruls and Torcilingi joined a rival who promised them land grants. A play by Friedrich D\u00a8urrenmatt focuses on the demise</b> <b>of this Roman emperor, who was overthrown by a former leader of the (+)</b> <em><b>federati</b></em><b> who</b> <b>went on to take over his capital. Julius Nepos disputed this man\u2019s claim to power. This man\u2019s father, Orestes, served (*) </b> Attila the Hun and appointed this man ruler at age 16. Odoacer overthrew, for ten points, what last emperor of the Western Roman Empire?", "answer": "<b> Romulus Augustulus</b> (or Flavius<b> Romulus Augustus</b>; prompt on \u201cRomulus the Great\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Al Franken wrote a speculative account of this election year titled</b><em><b> Why Not Me?</b></em><b>. \u201cThe Shrub\u201d led push-polling in South Carolina during this election year, during which David</b> <b>Foster Wallace reported for</b><em><b> Rolling Stone</b></em><b> while riding the (+)</b> <b>Straight Talk Express.</b> <b>Shortly before this election, a primary-loser released his memoir</b><em><b> Faith of My Fathers</b></em><b> about his service as a naval aviator in the (*)</b> Vietnam War. The eventual loser in this election year went on to win a Nobel Peace Prize in part for his book<em> An Inconvenient Truth</em>. For ten points, name this election year in which Al Gore lost to George W. Bush.", "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of<b> 2000</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This event was planned by Maurice Challe and Albert Gazier, who met with a Prime Minister at Chequers. During this event, Charles Keightley commanded an invasion in</b> <b>Operation Musketeer. The Protocol of (+)</b> <b>S\u00b4evres was a response to this crisis, which was</b> <b>caused in part by a withdrawal of funding by John Foster Dulles. The failure of the (*) </b>Franco-British intervention in this crisis led to the resignation of Anthony Eden. For ten points, name this 1956 crisis in which a European-backed Israeli invasion sought to capture a namesake waterway in Egypt.", "answer": "<b> Suez</b> Canal Crisis", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This event inspired, and is the subject of, the folk song \u201cRevenge for Skibbereen.\u201dWilliam Henry Gregory ensured that victims of this event who owned more than a quarter of an acre of land received no aid. Thousands of people who \u201ctook the (+) </b> <b>soup\u201d during this event made a choice between death and Catholicism. A typhus epidemic broke out in America as (*) </b> refugees from this event fled on \u201ccoffin ships.\u201d A huge influx of immigration to the US was driven by, for ten points, what 1840s disaster in which hundreds of thousands of Irish people starved to death?", "answer": "Irish<b> Potato Famine</b> (accept<b> An Gorta M\u00b4or</b>; accept<b> Great Famine</b>; prompt on famine alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}